Guide to the International Association of Machinists, Lodge 88 (Butte, Montana) Records 1915-1972
Montana Historical Society Archives
International Association of Machinists, Lodge 88 (Butte, Montana) Records
1915-1972
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 210
International Association of Machinists, Lodge 88 (Butte, Mont.)
2 linear feet of shelf space
Records of the International Association of Machinists, Lodge 88 (Butte, Montana) include general correspondence (1943-1953, 1967, 1969); financial records (1937-1970), including membership information; legal documents (1937-1960), consisting of labor agreements with employers; minutes (1915-1921, 1943-1959); reports (1944, 1947); subject files (1966-1967) pertaining to The Anaconda Company; and miscellany. [Artifacts have been transferred to the Museum.]
The Butte Machinist Union, International Association of Machinists, Lodge 88, was organized in Butte, Montana, in 1891. Officers included Master Machinist August Heimbach, Foreman Charles O'Rourke, Recording Secretary James Hamlin, and Treasurer Thomas Ogle.
Content Description:
Records. 1915-1972. 2 linear feet. The records of the International Association of Machinists, Lodge 88, of Butte, Montana, contain general correspondence (1943-1953, 1967, 1969); financial records (1937-1970), including memberhip information; legal documents (1937-1960), consisting of labor agreements with a variety of employers; minutes (1915-1921; 1943-1959); reports (1947); subject files (1966-1967) pertaining to The Anaconda Company; and miscellany. Artifacts have been transferred to the Museum.
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Machinists; Labor Unions; Butte (Mont.); Montana; Business, Industry, and Labor
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1943-1953, 1967,1969 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Financial Records
  - Annual report of receipts and disbursements, 1946 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Employers' monthly remittance reports (includes member's and employer's name, hours worked, etc.), July 1969- Dec. 1970 (Box-folder 1 / 3-5)
  - Employers' monthly remittance reports (includes member's and employer's name, hours worked, etc.), Jan-June, Nov-Dec. 1971; Jan 1972 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Receipts for bonds purchased, 1937-1954 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Treasurer's check stubs, Oct. 1946- Nov. 1949 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Treasurer's receipt book, Apr. 1951- Mar. 1953 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Treasurer's receipt book, Jan-July 1956 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Treasurer's receipt books, July 1956- Sept. 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 1-3)
  - Vouchers, 1954-1956 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
- Legal Documents
  - Labor agreements (includes agreements with the Sheep Shearers Merchandise and Commission Company; Silver Bow Employers' Association [OVERSIZE MATERIAL]; Western Iron Works, Inc.; The Montana Power Company; and the Northern Pacific Transport Company, 1937-1960 scattered (Box-folder 2 / 5-6)
- Minutes
  - Minute books, Oct. 1915- Apr. 1921 (Box-folder 2 / 7-8)
  - Minute books, Oct. 1943- June 1959 (Box-folder 3 / 1-7)
- Reports
  - Business agent's report, Nov. 1944 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Monthly report of vocational classes for auto mechanics and machinist apprentices (includes name of apprentices), Sept., Dec. 1947 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
- Subject Files
  - AFL-CIO Industril Union Department's Copper and Brass meeting (includes financial analysis, organizational status, selected contract provisions, and pension and insurance analyses of the Anaconda Company, and the Department's revised report on the Anaconda Company), Oct. 26-28, 1966 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Anaconda Company Joint Crafts Engineers and Teamsters Union (re pensions and health plans), 1966 (Box-folder 4 / 2-3)
  - Anaconda Company contract negotiations (includes "Agreement Between the Anaconda Company and...International Association of Machinists...", 1964), 1964, 1966 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
- Miscellany
  - Dues assignment authorization, 1965-1966, n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - "The Anaconda Company: Presentation to Special Panel Investigating the Copper Industry Strike", by R. Lewis Brown, Jr., Butte, and John Will, director of labor relations for the Anaconda Company, Feb. 1, 1968 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
  - The Anaconda Company strike referendum voters' list (includes sample ballot), June 18, 1971 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
  - List of artifacts transferred to the Museum (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - List of members not in good standing (May 26, 1954); list of International Association of Machinists' Helpers shop committeemen (Jan. 1921); list of Butte buildings and their type of heating system (1939); list of members (Oct. 1932), 1921-1954 scattered (Box-folder 4 / 9)
  - Medical insurance group policy, 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
  - Membership applications, 1938-1967 scattered (Box-folder 4 / 11)
  - "Provisions for Administration by State Apprenticeship Council of the State of Montana", 1941 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
  - Roll call book (includes lists of trustees and committees and apprentices started), 1918-1946 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
  - Voters' list for dues increase referendum (includes announcement of referendum), June 2, July 7,1966 (Box-folder 4 / 14)